<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The malignants lamentation in which all sorts of royalists, bemoan the miseries which have fallen upon them for taking up armes against the Parliament. Together with an acknowledgement of their former errors. Published according to order.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89442</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861039</idno>
  <idno type="VID">113166</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240886757</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E298_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200233</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861039</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99861039e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89442)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113166)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E298[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The malignants lamentation in which all sorts of royalists, bemoan the miseries which have fallen upon them for taking up armes against the Parliament. Together with an acknowledgement of their former errors. Published according to order.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 25".</note>
                  <note>Cropped at foot, affecting catchwords and some text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Royalists --  England --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113166:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> Clergy, and the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> as the <hi>Pope</hi> arrogateth to himselfe over the whole <hi>Christendome:</hi> which made him to keepe faire correspondency with the Queene, who pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed the Kings heart: and with the <hi>Pope</hi> himselfe, lest he should traverse his designe; but all this with a peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Do but observe, what cunning hath beene used to bring <hi>Popery</hi> again into <hi>England.</hi> Some demie Papists which were <hi>Jacobus Arminius</hi> Sectaries, did in the beginning of this Kings reigne preach, and maintaine Free-Will in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. Well, the businesse being scandalous, and too open, there was an order made, That none should either teach or preach such a doctrine, with a Proviso that none should preach against it. A thing much like unto the Order, which the <hi>Pope</hi> made concerning <hi>scientiamedia,</hi> and almost about the same time. They who preached against <hi>Arminianisme,</hi> were censured, but they, that preached for it, were tolerated in <hi>Bishop Williams</hi> time: but not during honest <hi>Abbots</hi> life. The doctrine of meritorious workes followed that of Free-Will. I have heard it maintained at a Commencement in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> by one Dr. <hi>Duncobm;</hi> and afterwards, one <hi>Roger</hi> did preach for the necessity of <hi>Auricular Confession.</hi> Were not these pretty preparations for the rest of the <hi>Popish</hi> er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours? The <hi>Pope</hi> having got so much, he changed his bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries; he sendes one <hi>Suta Clara</hi> to treat about agreement, that his Church, and ours might be but one. He knew that halfe of the eminent men in the Clergy were above halfe his already.</p>
            <p>Yet, all his plots could not prevaile for the totall ruine of the Protestant Religion in <hi>England.</hi> Many brave, pious, and learned Divines did preach against the errours, which were crept in too far amongst us: and they did give notice, and warning to the people, that <hi>Popery</hi> was at hand. Many heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto them, and joyned forces to oppose it, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther innovations in the State. The <hi>Popish</hi> faction perceiving
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113166:1"/>that their devises were like to be confounded; went another way to worke; they perswaded the King to leave his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon a pretended feare of his owne Person, to go to raise forces in the Country; knowing that their were a good many, who were altogether <hi>Papists;</hi> and others who did not care much for Religion; who fearing a Reformation, would rather joyne with them, than to adhere to the Parliament. Great assistance was expected from beyond seas; but it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God, that some, who were solicited to send ayde to the King, would send none; and that others could not send any, by reason of the warres they had themselves. Now, if the King had shewed himselfe at the very first a favourer of the <hi>Popish</hi> party, and inclining to an arbitrary government; most of them, who followed him, would have left him: because, few men desire to fight to bring themselves into slavery: and moreover many, who were none of the best <hi>Protestants,</hi> were loath to advance the <hi>Popish</hi> Religion: but the way to make all the <hi>Protestant</hi> cavaliers to believe, that the King was one of theirs; was to possesse the great ones, and especially some of the honest sort of Clergy-men with that opinion.</p>
            <p>The old Bishop of <hi>Armagh</hi> was cudgell'd into that beliefe: The King protested in his presence, in <hi>Christ-Church</hi> at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> that he would maintaine the Protestant Religion, and tooke the Sacrament upon it; I know not how the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Religion can be well maintained when the Papists are favoured, and when the King is constant to the Queeneu grounds, and documents. That Bishop being one of the preaching Bishops, and a man of good and honest conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being first deceived, deceived many thousands more. As for those, who had rather to loose <hi>Christ</hi> than their hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours; and who had rather to be <hi>Popish</hi> Bishops, than no Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, we meddle not with them; nor with any one else, who is not a true <hi>Protestant</hi> indeed. For, it cannot be said that they were deceived, by reason that things have proved according to their expectation.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:113166:2"/>
            <p> But alas for us poore silly, and ignorant men, could wee thinke otherwise, but that our King meant as he said, when our Parsons, &amp; Curates did read so bravely his fine Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Protestations after Evening prayers, although our minds were either for cudgell-playes, for dauncing, and pipeing, and for drinking of a cup of good-ale as soone as we could get out of the Church, and before the Priest could have put off his surplice. Yet, we stayed longer very willingly to heare them read; and if they had beene twice as long as they were, we would not have been weary a jot. If we had heard any one of the Round-heads pray, but halfe so long, we would have left him to preach to the vvalls. We heard so many times the <hi>Preservation</hi> of the <hi>Protestant Religion;</hi> the <hi>redemption</hi> of our <hi>brethren in Ireland;</hi> the <hi>happinesse,</hi> and <hi>prosperity</hi> of these <hi>Kingdomes;</hi> and the <hi>dignity,</hi> and <hi>freedome</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> named in the Kings declarations, vvith Protestations of his Majestie to defend and maintaine all these things: That vve vvould have beene very hard of beliefe, if we had not given credit unto his words: nay, most of our Land lords told us, that they were very true, and that the Kings heart went along with his mouth. And we can tell you, that many of them were men of good understanding, and of note. Why? Some were Bishops, Doctors in Divinity, brave Deanes, rich Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and Prebends; we thought that these men would have knowne the Kings mind: because, we knew that he loved them intirely. But alas! they are deluded as well we; and they are in a worse case, than we are: for, they shalbe no more what they were, and we may perhaps be once in a better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, than we are now.</p>
            <p>Yet we must confesse ingeniously that vve vvere not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether so ignorant, but that vve knevv, or at least doubted of something. For vve heard some of the Parliaments Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions read, and many good, and honest Divines, and others told us, that the <hi>Jesuites</hi> vvere very povverfull in the Kings privie Councell; That <hi>Popery</hi> vvas a comming in apace, if <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113166:2"/>
            <p> Now gentlemen, you that are of the true Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and who are not ill-affected to the publike good of your owne Country; but are a litle led away by your owne private Interests, by vain hopes of preferments, and have been deceived by the Kings faire Protestations. If you understand your selves well; make use of your former mis-understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and plead <hi>Ignoramus.</hi> The King does in his letters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare you not guilty in some points; and therefore you may with your honour submit your selves to the Parliaments mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, who will pittie you like ignorant, and decieved men: if by your sudden returning to your duty; you shew that you are willing to leave a bad party, when you know it to be so: and to believe the truth, when it is evidently manifested unto you. Seeke not for excuses to make the matter better, than it is. The King hath made a bridge for you, to come all to the Parliament: And now especially that he is with his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sens the <hi>Welsh-men.</hi> His Majestie, that has detained you so long with him, with his faire words, cannot keepe you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force.</p>
            <p>Now I heare the Complaint of other Cavaliers, who are meere Carnall men. Alas! alas! say they, we tooke up armes, because wee would not suffer the Round-heads to pull downe our crosses, our babies, and our Organs; and to take the surplices from our Priests. Was it not a very fine thing, to go of a Sunday in the afternoone, to heare the Organs, and many other brave instruments of musicke in some Cathedral Church: and to see the Deane, the Canons, the singing-men, and the very Cheristers boyes in fine surplices? It was a fine thing indeed, and much like unto a play. Whilest the eare was ravished with the melody of musicke, the heart did litle thinke of God. We lost much now, that Clergy-men weare no surplices; for our wives got them many times to make clouts, and now wee must buy them new ones. But our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, that Clergy-men visit not our wives so often as they did in former time. Alas! wee would rather have lost our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113166:3"/>lives, than to see our May-poles put downe; what a cruell thing is this, that we must have no more playes, no more <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdancers,</hi> and no more Whit-sunday-ale? what all sports taken away from us? but the worst is, that we cannot reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it. The Round-heads are growne so strong, that we cannot withstand them: vve are affraid that vve must all turne Round or else it vvill be vvorse for us. That's the onely thing, that vexes us vvorst of all; vve could finde in our hearts to be vvith them, if they vvould but alovv us our former sports, and pastimes.</p>
            <p>Some others complaine thus. Alas! vve thought vvhen vve did first take up armes, that the King vvould get the mastery over the Parliament vvithin a very short time. They made us to believe it at least.</p>
            <p>We vvere told after the taking of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> the routing of Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> and of my Lord <hi>Fairfaxes armie:</hi> that the businesse was as good as done: and that we should see <hi>London</hi> shortly. Alas! many of us do see it now to our griefe, and in another way than we expected. All our trouble was afore to thinke upon what street in <hi>London</hi> we should have fallen first. For, they amongst us, who knew <hi>London,</hi> had all a mind to <hi>Cheapside,</hi> and to <hi>Lumbard</hi> street; because they thought to find there, more money ready coined than else-where: and vve vvho heard them naming those tvvo streets, said vvithin our selves vve vvill be in them as soone as you, for all your hast. I thinke it is vvell, that vve have not taken <hi>London;</hi> for I believe that vve should have slaine one another for bootie-sake.</p>
            <p>The businesse of <hi>Glocester,</hi> and the besieging of <hi>Hull</hi> sticks still to our stomacks. Yet vvee vvere in a pretty vvay after our victory in the <hi>West.</hi> We marched fast enough towards <hi>London,</hi> but they stopt us at <hi>Dennington;</hi> yet wee did passe afterwards: let that passe: our new, and greatest hopes were, that whilest their new armie was a raising; we would have advanced, and made use of the unsetlement of their affaires.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113166:3"/>But nothing prospers with us, surely God is not with us, and we do not fight for his Cause. For, in all humane probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, vve have had many advantages over the Round-heads; and yet they are novv more povverfull than ever they vvere: our commanders told us afore <hi>Naseby</hi> fight, that Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> Armie consisted of men, that knevv better hovv to pray, than hovv to fight: vvhich made us to believe that the day vvould be ours; but vve vvere deceived, for they did fight vvith as much earnest, as they could ever have pray'd: our horse left us in the lurch, and that Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> vvhom vve thought to be so couragious, and so valiant, did spurre his horse as quicke as any of the rest. But alas! our last hopes is gone: <hi>Goring</hi> is beaten by Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax:</hi> vve that vvere ever conquerours in the <hi>West,</hi> do begin to be conquered there. The very club-men rise against our men: Wee might expect some reliefe from <hi>Wales,</hi> but the blevv-bonners are too neere the <hi>Welsh;</hi> the Kings boats are taken, and they keepe him from passing the <hi>Severne</hi> over againe.</p>
            <p>What lamentable businesse is this? What pittifull passe are vve come to? Wee that vvere but ordinary fellovves did make full account to be made gentlemen at least by the King. We that were but esquires did looke for a knight-hood. We that were lords could not expect any thing lesse than to be made earles: and we that were earles already, did aspire to the honour of Marquesses. Well, some of us have got such dignities, as we did looke for: but, where have we meanes to live, and to maintaine a traine accordingly? we would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly give the King his new titles back againe; if he would but restore us the money, they cost us. We are like those whom they call the Kings Doctors, who buy their degrees with money, and are litle regarded afterwards by the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie. For indeed, we have (most of us) taken our new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Believe me Gentlemen, you have beene very simple to hope for great preferments, and for large rewards from the King;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113166:4"/>If he had got the day by the sword, you know that the Jewels of his Crowne are in pawne; and you are not ignorant that it was fit that he should redeeme his owne, before he could thinke of satisfying others. They, unto whom he was most ingaged (to wit the Papists) would have look't to be reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed first of all: and then afterwards some few of your Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants would have had what they could catch; and some no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all: most of you, did thinke to be one time or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Kings favourites. I dare say, that if things had proved according to the expectation of his Majestie: the very Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers would have raised warres against them, some out of vexation to see themselves deluded, and undone; and some out of spight to see others preferred afore them.</p>
            <p>Let it be for the comfort of you that are Protestants, that you had bin all undone in your liberties, Estates, &amp; Religion, if the Kings partie had not beene undone; you shall find at last, that you are, and have beene beholding to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who have sought hitherto to preserve your persons from a <hi>Popish</hi> slavery; and your estates, from an Arbitrary government. You shall once confesse (I trust) that they have been better to you, than you have bin to your selves in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pernicious leaders. They look for the generall good of this Kingdome which is intrusted to them: of which you must needs participate soon, or late, if you will be ruled by them.</p>
            <p>Now, for the <hi>Welsh</hi> Cavaliers complaint in <hi>Tuttle</hi> fields. What do you talke to her of Religion? her is, and will be still of her Cozen the King his Religion. Her stands not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on scruples, nor understand not what scruples meane: her is vexed for nothing but that her Cozen the King is not come along with her to <hi>London.</hi> Her was told that her should see her Cozens fine house, which they call <hi>White-hall;</hi> her did see nothing but the wals of it: her was told, that her would get money, to buy her a fine suite of cloathes, gilded spurres, a beaver, with a plume of feathers, and a sword to walke like a gentleman as her was borne: and that her should live in a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113166:4"/>brave house: but her lies upon the ground, hath no cloathes, and is still bare-foot, as her was in her owne Country. Her Cozen was very unkind to ride away from her, and to leave her amongst the Roundheads. If her had had but a horse as well as some of the rest, her woud have rode away into her owne Country, where her would have stollen a sheepe or two, but her would have made her Cozen welcome.</p>
            <p>But alas for us power Papists! we are in the very worst case of all. We have spent, and wasted our meanes to helpe the King, and we see now, that he cannot helpe himselfe, nor us neither. We have beene deceived as well, nay worse, than the rest. For, although the end of our helping the King, was to set up our Religion, and to destroy the Protestants totally Yet, we must needs say, that we love honours, dignities, and wealth as well as the rest. We had large promises made unto us, and we were fed up with brave hopes: we made full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to see all Penall Statutes against us repealed, and now they will be put in execution more than afore. We thought to see shortly, that the way to come to preferment would have beene to turne <hi>Papists;</hi> and that none but they that would go to Masse, should have beene regarded: we were told that it would be shortly <hi>La mode de la Cour.</hi> And now we see that we must go over into <hi>Ireland, France, Italy,</hi> or <hi>Spaine</hi> to heare Masse. But how shall we live there? shall we beg in <hi>France?</hi> they have beggers enough of their owne; and besides, the <hi>French</hi> Catholiques are not so well affected to us. As for the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> Alas poore people! how can they helpe us, when they have much a do to live themselves; now that they have warres in so many places with the <hi>French?</hi> But perhaps our holy father, and his blessed Cardinals will relieve us. Alas! alas! The <hi>Pope,</hi> and all his Cardinals have need of their moneyes to defend themselves against the <hi>Turke.</hi> And moreover, (though we be never so great Catholiques) vvee must confesse ingeniously that the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the Cardinalls vvould make us more vvelcome if vve should carry money to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113166:5"/>
               <hi>Rome,</hi> than if vve should go thither peny-lesse. We might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect some comfort from our Brethren in <hi>Ireland;</hi> but that vve knovv, that they are a lasie nation, vvho vvould rather live upon other men; than to extend their charity upon others. They have litle enough for themselves, their Country having beene the stage of vvarres these foure yeares. We cannot tell vvhat to do, and vve knovv not vvhich vvay to turne our selves; vve have no heart to turne Protestants, novv that they have pull'd dovvne Images, and that we can neither heare the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans play, nor see the Priests with their surplices, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with their copes; for, then we did in a manner thinke we were at masse, and many of us did expect to heare a masse after all that brave service. And now, we can heare nothing but a minister praying, and preaching the Word of God, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and expounding many passages of the Scripture in our owne mothers tongue; we had rather to heare our Priests speake them in <hi>Latin,</hi> as we wonted to do, that we might not understand them.</p>
            <p>Now you that are Malignants, you may plainly see that God is not for you, and that he will maintain his cause against all your plots and conspiracies: you see how he prospereth Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> his honest Army. <hi>Round dealings</hi> used to be best afore these Wars, and will be so still when the Wars are ended. As for you that are Papists, if God hath not as yet enlightned your darknesse, if you know not the errours of your Superstition; yet resolve to leave off plotting against your own native Country, wean your selves from the fond love you have to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and to the Jesuites: and by these meanes (If the Parliament be pleased to take you to mercy) you may in Gods due time, enjoy a peaceable tranquility with us in our sweet <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113166:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>